We most certainly do talk to terrorists, no question about it.
لابد وأننا نتحدث عن الإرهابيين، ما من شك في ذلك.
We are at war with a new form of terrorism.
نحن في حالة حرب مع شكل جديد للإرهاب.
It's sort of the good old, traditional form of terrorism,
إنه نوعاً ما شكل قديم وتقليدي،
but it's sort of been packaged for the 21st century.
لكنه، بصورةٍ ما، كان نوعاً مُعدّاً للقرن الواحد العشرين.
One of the big things about countering terrorism
أحد أهم الأمور في مواجهة الإرهاب
is, how do you perceive it?
هو تصوركم عنه.
Because perception leads to your response to it.
لأن الإدراك يؤثر على ردود أفعالكم تجاهه.
So if you have a traditional perception of terrorism,
فإذا كان لديكم تصور تقليدي عن الإرهاب،
it would be that it's one of criminality, one of war.
فسيكون متعلقاً بالجرائم، بالحروب.
So how are you going to respond to it?
فكيف ستكون ردة فعلكم تجاهه؟
Naturally, it would follow that you meet kind with kind.
ردة فعلكم ستتبع، بشكل طبيعي، سياسة "الجزاء من جنس العمل".
You fight it. If you have a more modernist approach,
ستحاربونه. وإن كنتم تتبعون منهجاً أكثر حداثة،
and your perception of terrorism is almost cause-and-effect,
وكان تصوركم عن الإرهاب له علاقة بالسبب والنتيجة،
then naturally from that, the responses that come out of it
فـ كنتيجة طبيعية لذلك، ردود أفعالكم تجاهه
are much more asymmetrical.
ستكون، إلى حد كبير، غير متماثلة (لا تماثل الفعل).
We live in a modern, global world.
نحن نعيش في عالم حديث وشامل.
Terrorists have actually adapted to it.
وقد تكيف الإرهابيون معه بالفعل.
It's something we have to, too, and that means the people
ولابد لنا أيضاً أن نتكيف معه، ويعني هذا أن على الأشخاص
who are working on counterterrorism responses
الذين يعملون على مكافحة الإرهاب
have to start, in effect, putting on
أن يبدأوا، فعلياً، مرتدين
their Google-tinted glasses, or whatever.
نظارات قوقل الملونة الخاصة بهم، أو مهما كان.
For my part, what I wanted us to do was just to look at
من جهتي، كل ما أردته هو أن ننظر
terrorism as though it was a global brand,
للإرهاب كما لو كان علامة تجارية عالمية،
say, Coca-Cola.
كوكا كولا مثلاً.
Both are fairly bad for your health. (Laughter)
كلاهما مُضِّر بالصحة. (ضحك)
If you look at it as a brand in those ways,
إن نظرتم إليه كعلامة تجارية من هذه النواحي،
what you'll come to realize is, it's a pretty flawed product.
فإنكم ستُدركون أنه منتج معيب جداً.
As we've said, it's pretty bad for your health,
وكما قلنا، الإرهاب له تأثير سيء جداً على الصحة،
it's bad for those who it affects,
سيء على من يتأذى منه،
and it's not actually good if you're a suicide bomber either.
وهو كذلك سيء عليك إن كنت مفجراً انتحارياً.
It doesn't actually do what it says on the tin.
إنه ليس كما يروّج عنه.
You're not really going to get 72 virgins in heaven.
فلن تحظوا باثنتان وسبعين بكراً في الجنة.
It's not going to happen, I don't think.
لا أعتقد أن هذا سيحدث.
And you're not really going to, in the '80s, end capitalism
ولن تقوموا، في الثمانينات، بإنهاء الرأسمالية
by supporting one of these groups. It's a load of nonsense.
من خلال دعمكم لأحد هذه الجماعات. هذا غير منطقي.
But what you realize, it's got an Achilles' heel.
لكنكم ستلاحظون أن للإرهاب نقطة ضعف مميتة.
The brand has an Achilles' heel.
للعلامة التجارية نقطة ضعف مدمرة.
We've mentioned the health,
أشرنا إلى الصحة،
but it needs consumers to buy into it.
لكنها تحتاج إلى زبائن ليستثمروا فيها.
The consumers it needs are the terrorist constituency.
الزبائن الذين تحتاجهم هذه العلامة هم الإرهابيين المتماسكين.
They're the people who buy into the brand, support them,
هم الأشخاص الذين يستثمروا في الإرهاب، وهم من يدعم الإرهابيين
facilitate them, and they're the people
ويساعدونهم، وهم من
we've got to reach out to.
يبنغي أن نمد لهم يد العون.
We've got to attack that brand in front of them.
يجب أن نهاجم تلك العلامة التجارية أمامهم.
There's two essential ways of doing that, if we carry on this brand theme.
هناك طريقتين أساسيتين للقيام بذلك،
One is reducing their market. What I mean is,
أحدهما تكون بالحد من تجارتهم. ما أعنيه هو،
it's their brand against our brand. We've got to compete.
أن علامتهم التجارية ضد علامتنا التجارية، علينا أنا ننافسهم.
We've got to show we're a better product.
علينا أن نثبت أننا نملك منتجاً أفضل.
If I'm trying to show we're a better product,
إن كنت أحاول أن أظهر أن منتجنا أفضل،
I probably wouldn't do things like Guantanamo Bay.
لن أقوم على الأرجح بفعل شيء مثل خليج غوانتانامو.
We've talked there about curtailing the underlying need
لقد تحدثنا عن إنهاء الحاجة الأساسية
for the product itself. You could be looking there at
للمنتج نفسه. قد تنظرون
poverty, injustice, all those sorts of things
إلى الفقر، الظلم، وكل هذه الأمور
which feed terrorism.
التي تغذي الإرهاب.
The other thing to do is to knock the product,
الطريقة الثانية تكون بالتقليل من قيمة المنتج،
attack the brand myth, as we've said.
مهاجمة أسطورة العلامة التجارية، كما قلنا.
You know, there's nothing heroic about killing a young kid.
كما تعلمون، قتل الأطفال الصغار لايحمل أي صفة بطولية.
Perhaps we need to focus on that and get that message back across.
ربما نحتاج إلى التركيز على ذلك وإلى إعادة نشر تلك الرسالة.
We've got to reveal the dangers in the product.
علينا أن نكشف خطورة هذا المنتج.
Our target audience, it's not just the producers of terrorism,
جمهورنا المستهدف لايقتصر فقط على منتجي الإرهاب،
as I've said, the terrorists.
الإرهابين، كما قلت.
It's not just the marketeers of terrorism,
ولا نستهدف فقط مسوّقي الإرهاب،
which is those who finance, those who facilitate it,
أولئك الذين يدعمون الإرهاب ويقدمون التسهيلات له،
but it's the consumers of terrorism.
لكنه أيضاً يشمل المستهلكين للإرهاب.
We've got to get in to those homelands.
علينا أن نتوغل في تلك المواطن،
That's where they recruit from. That's where they get their power and strength.
حيث يتم تجنيدهم، وحيث يحصلون منها على قوتهم وسلطتهم.
That's where their consumers come from.
من هناك يأتي زبائنهم.
And we have to get our messaging in there.
وعلينا أن ننشر رسالتنا هنا.
So the essentials are, we've got to have interaction
قواعدنا إذن هي، أن يكون لنا تفاعل
in those areas, with the terrorists, the facilitators, etc.
في تلك المناطق، مع الإرهابيين، والميسرين، الخ.
We've got to engage, we've got to educate,
علينا أن ننخرط معهم، أن نثقفهم،
and we've got to have dialogue.
وأن نتحاور معهم.
Now, staying on this brand thing for just a few more seconds,
والآن، مع استمرار حديثنا عن هذه العلامة التجارية لبضع ثواني،
think about delivery mechanisms.
فكروا في آلية التنفيذ.
How are we going to do these attacks?
كيف سنقوم بنتفيذ هذه الهجمات؟
Well, reducing the market is really one for governments
حسناً، الحد من السوق هي خطوة تقوم بها الحكومات
and civil society. We've got to show we're better.
والمجتمع المدني, علينا أن نظهر أننا أفضل.
We've got to show our values.
علينا أن نظهر قيمنا.
We've got to practice what we preach.
علينا أن نطبق ما ننصح الآخرين به.
But when it comes to knocking the brand,
لكن عندما يتعلق الامر بالتقليل من قيمة العلامة التجارية،
if the terrorists are Coca-Cola and we're Pepsi,
إن كان الإرهابيين هم شركة كوكا كولا ونحن شركة بيبسي،
I don't think, being Pepsi, anything we say about Coca-Cola,
لا أظن أحداً سيصدق مانقول عن كوكاكولا،
anyone's going to believe us.
كوننا شركة مشابهة.
So we've got to find a different mechanism,
لذا علينا أن نجد آلية مختلفة.
and one of the best mechanisms I've ever come across
وأحد أفضل الآليات التي اكتشفتها مصادفة
is the victims of terrorism.
تتمثل في ضحايا الإرهاب.
They are somebody who can actually stand there and say,
هم أي أحد قد يقف ويقول،
"This product's crap. I had it and I was sick for days.
"هذا منتج سئ. مرضت بسببه لعدة أيام.
It burnt my hand, whatever." You believe them.
حرقت يدي، أو أياً يكن." ستصدقونهم.
You can see their scars. You trust them.
يمكنكم أن تروا آثار جروحهم. أنتم تثقون بهم.
But whether it's victims, whether it's governments,
لكن سواء الضحايا، الحكومات،
NGOs, or even the Queen yesterday, in Northern Ireland,
المنظمات الغير حكومية، أو حتى الملكة، في شمال ايرلندا،
we have to interact and engage with those different
علينا أن نتفاعل و نندمج مع طبقات الإرهاب
layers of terrorism, and, in effect,
المختلفة تلك، وفي الواقع،
we do have to have a little dance with the devil.
علينا أن نرقص قليلاً مع الشيطان.
This is my favorite part of my speech.
هذا هو الجزء المفضل لي من حديثي.
I wanted to blow you all up to try and make a point,
أردت أن أُفقدكم صوابكم لهدف،
but — (Laughter) —
لكن - (ضحك) -
TED, for health and safety reasons, have told me
لكن مؤسسة TED أخبرتي، لأسباب صحية وأمنية،
I've got to do a countdown, so
أن علي أن أقوم بعد تنازلي، لذا
I feel like a bit of an Irish or Jewish terrorist,
أشعر وكأني ارهابي إيرلندي أو يهودي،
sort of a health and safety terrorist, and I — (Laughter) —
إرهابي له علاقة بالأمن والصحة، و - (ضحك) -
I've got to count 3, 2, 1, and
علي أن أقوم بالعد من 1،2،3، و
it's a bit alarming, so thinking of what my motto would be,
هذا مرعب قليلاً، لذا فإن شعاري سيكون
and it would be, "Body parts, not heart attacks."
"أجزاء الجسم، وليس نوبات قلبية."
So 3, 2, 1. (Explosion sound)
لذا 1،2،3 (صوت انفجار)
Very good. (Laughter)
ممتاز. (ضحك)
Now, lady in 15J was a suicide bomber amongst us all.
والآن، على مقعد ياء15 كانت تجلس سيدة انتحارية بيننا جميعا.
We're all victims of terrorism.
كلنا ضحايا للإرهاب.
There's 625 of us in this room. We're going to be scarred for life.
يوجد في هذا المكان 625 شخص. لن ننسى ذلك أبداً.
There was a father and a son who sat in that seat over there.
كان هناك أب مع ابنه كانا يجلسان على ذلك المقعد هناك.
The son's dead. The father lives.
قُتل الابن، وعاش الأب.
The father will probably kick himself for years to come
الوالد من المتوقع ان يلوم نفسه لسنوات.
that he didn't take that seat instead of his kid.
أنه لم يأخذ ذلك المقعد بدلا من طفله.
He's going to take to alcohol, and he's probably
سيدمن على الشراب، وقد يُقدم
going to kill himself in three years. That's the stats.
على قتل نفسه خلال ثلاث سنوات. هذا ماقد يحصل.
There's a very young, attractive lady over here,
تقف هناك شابة جميلة جداً،
and she has something which I think's the worst form
وهي مصابة بما أظنها أسوأ
of psychological, physical injury I've ever seen
إصابة نفسية وجسدية شهدتها في حياتي
out of a suicide bombing: It's human shrapnel.
بسبب التفجير الانتحاري: أنها شظايا بشرية.
What it means is, when she sat in a restaurant
وهذا يعني أنها عندما تجلس في مطعم
in years to come, 10 years to come, 15 years to come,
في السنوات القادمة، في العشر السنوات القادمة، في السنوات الخمسة عشر القادمة،
or she's on the beach, every so often she's going to start
أو عندما تكون على الشاطئ، وستبدأ على الغالب
rubbing her skin, and out of there will come
بتنظيف بشرتها، ومن هناك ستظهر
a piece of that shrapnel.
قطعة من تلك الشظايا.
And that is a hard thing for the head to take.
وهذا شيء يصعب تحمله.
There's a lady over there as well who lost her legs
وهناك أيضاً سيدة هناك فقدت ساقيها
in this bombing.
في ذلك الإنفجار.
She's going to find out that she gets a pitiful amount
و ستجد أنها حصلت على مبالغ تافهة
of money off our government
قدمتها الحكومة
for looking after what's happened to her.
للعناية بها بعد الحادثة.
She had a daughter who was going to go to one of the best
لديها ابنة كانت ستنضم إلى واحدة من أفضل
universities. She's going to give up university
الجامعات. ستظطر لترك الجامعة
to look after Mum.
كي تعتني بأمها.
We're all here, and all of those who watch it
جميعنا و جميع من سيشاهد الحدث
are going to be traumatized by this event,
سنصاب الصدمة بسببه،
but all of you here who are victims are going to learn
لكن جميع الضحايا سيتعلمون
some hard truths.
بعض الحقائق الصعبة.
That is, our society, we sympathize, but after a while,
وهي، أن مجتمعنا يتعاطف لكن بعد فترة،
we start to ignore. We don't do enough as a society.
يبدأ المجتمع بالتجاهل. نحن لا نقوم بما يكفي كمجتمع.
We do not look after our victims, and we do not enable them,
نحن لا نعتني بضحايانا، ولا نمكنهم من ذلك،
and what I'm going to try and show is that actually,
وما سأقوم بتوضيحه في الواقع هو
victims are the best weapon we have
أن الضحايا هم أفضل سلاح نستطيع من خلاله
against more terrorism.
مواجهة الارهاب.
How would the government at the turn of the millennium
كيف تناولت الحكومة الأمر
approach today? Well, we all know.
مع مطلع الألفية؟ حسنًا، جميعنا نعرف.
What they'd have done then is an invasion.
ماقامت به الحكومات حينها هو الغزو.
If the suicide bomber was from Wales,
إن كان المفجر الإنتحاري من ويلز،
good luck to Wales, I'd say.
فسأقول، حظًا طيبًا لويلز.
Knee-jerk legislation, emergency provision legislation --
القانون الغير محسوب و قانون الطوارئ
which hits at the very basis of our society, as we all know --
الذي أصاب أساس المجتمع، كما نعرف جميعنا،
it's a mistake.
يٌعد خطأً.
We're going to drive prejudice throughout Edinburgh,
ستقوم بنقل التعصب عبر أدنبرة،
throughout the U.K., for Welsh people.
وعبر الممكلة المتحدة لسكان ويلز.
Today's approach, governments have learned from their mistakes.
التعلم من الأخطاء هو منهج الحكومات اليوم.
They are looking at what I've started off on,
إنها تنظر إلى ما أشرت إليه في البداية،
on these more asymmetrical approaches to it,
إلى تلك الأساليب التي لا تتماثل معها،
more modernist views, cause and effect.
أراء أكثر حداثة، السبب والنتيجة.
But mistakes of the past are inevitable.
لكن أخطاء الماضي لا مفر منها.
It's human nature.
إنها طبيعة بشرية.
The fear and the pressure to do something on them
الخوف منها والضغط الناتج عن ضرورة مواجهتها
is going to be immense. They are going to make mistakes.
سيكون هائلاً. سيقومون بارتكاب الأخطاء.
They're not just going to be smart.
لن يكونوا أذكياء فحسب.
There was a famous Irish terrorist who once summed up
كان هناك إرهابي إيرلندي لخّص مرةً
the point very beautifully. He said,
هذه الفكرة بشكل جميل جداً عندما قال:
"The thing is, about the British government, is, is that it's got
"المسألة هي، أن على الحكومة البريطانية
to be lucky all the time, and we only have to be lucky once."
أن تكون محظوظة دائماً، وأن علينا أن نكون محظوظون مرة واحدة."
So what we need to do is we have to effect it.
لذا، فإن ما علينا فعله هو أن نؤثر فيها.
We've got to start thinking about being more proactive.
علينا أن نفكر في أن نكون فاعلين أكثر.
We need to build an arsenal of noncombative weapons
علينا أن ننشئ ترسانة من الأسلحة الغير مقاتلة
in this war on terrorism.
في حربنا على الإرهاب.
But of course, it's ideas -- is not something that governments do very well.
لكن بالطبع، فكرة هذه الحرب لا تجيدها الحكومات جيداً.
I want to go back just to before the bang, to this idea of
أريد فقط ان أعود إلى ماقبل الإنفجار، إلى فكرة
brand, and I was talking about Coke and Pepsi, etc.
العلامة التجارية، عندما كنت أتحدث عن كوكا كولا وبيبسي، الخ.
We see it as terrorism versus democracy in that brand war.
في تلك الحرب نرى أنها حرب بين الإرهاب والديموقراطية.
They'll see it as freedom fighters and truth
وهم سيرونها حرب الحرية والحقيقة
against injustice, imperialism, etc.
ضد الظلم والإمبريالية، الخ.
We do have to see this as a deadly battlefield.
علينا ان ننظر لهذه الحرب كمعركة مميتة.
It's not just [our] flesh and blood they want.
مايريدونه ليس دمنا ولحمنا فحسب.
They actually want our cultural souls, and that's why
هم في الحقيقية يريدون روحنا الثقافية، ولهذا السبب
the brand analogy is a very interesting way of looking at this.
التمثيل بالعلامة التجارية طريقة مثيرة جداً للنظر في هذا الأمر.
If we look at al Qaeda. Al Qaeda was essentially
لو نظرنا إلى القاعدة. القاعدة كانت أساساً
a product on a shelf in a souk somewhere
منتج على أحد الرفوف في سوق في مكانٍ ما
which not many people had heard of.
لم يسمع به كثير من الناس.
9/11 launched it. It was its big marketing day,
أطلقته أحداث 11/9. كان يومها التسويقي الكبير،
and it was packaged for the 21st century. They knew what they were doing.
وكانت مٌعدة للقرن الواحد والعشرين. كانوا يعرفون ماكانوا يفعلون.
They were effectively [doing] something in this brand image
كانوا يصنعون صورة لهذه العلامة بشكل فعّال
of creating a brand which can be franchised around
لخلق علامة تجارية يمكن تلزيمها حول
the world, where there's poverty, ignorance and injustice.
العالم، حيث يوجد الفقر والجهل والظلم.
We, as I've said, have got to hit that market,
كما قلت، علينا أن نضرب هذه التجارة،
but we've got to use our heads rather than our might.
لكن علينا أن نستخدم عقولنا بدلاً من قوتنا.
If we perceive it in this way as a brand, or other ways of thinking at it like this,
إذا نظرنا إليها بهذه الطريقة كعلامة تجارية، أو طريقة أخرى،
we will not resolve or counter terrorism.
لن نتمكن من مواجهة الإرهاب أو التخلص منه.
What I'd like to do is just briefly go through a few examples
ما سأقوم به هو عرض بعض الأمثلة باختصار
from my work on areas where we try and approach these things differently.
من عملي على بعض المجالات حيث نحاول أن نتناول هذه المسائل بشكل مختلف.
The first one has been dubbed "lawfare,"
تمت تسمية المثال الأول بـ "حرب القانون"
for want of a better word.
لعدم وجود كلمة أفضل.
When we originally looked at bringing civil actions against terrorists,
عندما فكرنا أولاً في رفع دعاوى مدنية ضد الإرهابيين،
everyone thought we were a bit mad and mavericks
اعتقد الجميع أننا مجانين ومعتوهون
and crackpots. Now it's got a title. Everyone's doing it.
أصبحت الآن حقاً شرعياً. الكل يقوم بذلك.
There's a bomb, people start suing.
هناك تفجير، يبدأ الناس بعدها برفع الدعاوى.
But one of the first early cases on this was the Omagh Bombing.
لكن أحد القضايا الأولى حول هذا الموضوع كانت تفجير أوما.
A civil action was brought from 1998.
تم توجيه دعوى مدنية من عام 1998.
In Omagh, bomb went off, Real IRA,
في أوما، انفجرت قنبلة، على يد الجيش الجمهوري الإيرلندي الحقيقي،
middle of a peace process.
في منتصف عملية السلام.
That meant that the culprits couldn't really be prosecuted
وهذا يعني أنه لايمكن رفع دعاوى قضائية ضد الجناة
for lots of reasons, mostly to do with the peace process
لعدة أسباب، معظمها متعلقة بعملية السلام
and what was going on, the greater good.
وماكان يجري، تجاه المصلحة العليا.
It also meant, then, if you can imagine this,
وهذا يعني أيضاً، إن استعطتم تخيل هذا،
that the people who bombed your children
أن الأشخاص الذين فجروا أطفالكم
and your husbands were walking around the supermarket
وأزواجكم كانوا يمشون حول المتجر
that you lived in.
الذي تعيش بقربه.
Some of those victims said enough is enough.
قال بعض أولئك الضحايا أنهم اكتفوا من ذلك.
We brought a private action, and thank God, 10 years later,
قمنا بتوجيه دعوى خاصة، والحمدلله، بعد عشر سنوات
we actually won it. There is a slight appeal on
ربحناها بالفعل.
at the moment so I have to be a bit careful,
الآن لذا علي أن أكون حذراً قليلاً
but I'm fairly confident.
لكني واثق جداً.
Why was it effective?
لماذا كانت فعّالة؟
It was effective not just because justice was seen to be done
لم تكن فعالة فقط لأن العدالة كان لابد أن تأخذ مجراها
where there was a huge void.
في ظل الفساد الهائل.
It was because the Real IRA and other terrorist groups,
إنما بسبب أن الجيش الجمهوري الإيرلندي الحقيقي و جماعات ارهابية أخرى
their whole strength is from the fact that they are
كانوا يستمدون قوتهم من حقيقة أنهم
an underdog. When we put the victims as the underdog
مضطهدون. عندما عكسنا الصورة ووضعنا الضحايا
and flipped it, they didn't know what to do.
مكانهم، لم يعرفوا ماذا يفعلون.
They were embarrassed. Their recruitment went down.
كانوا مُحرجين. ضاع تجنيدهم سُدى.
The bombs actually stopped -- fact -- because of this action.
توقفت التفجيرات في الواقع -- حقيقة -- بسبب هذه الدعوى.
We became, or those victims became, more importantly,
أصبحنا، أو الأهم، أصبح أولئك الضحايا
a ghost that haunted the terrorist organization.
أشباح تتلبس التنظيم الإرهابي.
There's other examples. We have a case called Almog
هناك مثال اخر. كانت لدينا قضيه تدعى الومق.
which is to do with a bank that was,
التي لها علاقه بالبنك الذي،
allegedly, from our point of view,
يُزعم، من وجهة نظرنا،
giving rewards to suicide bombers.
يعطي مكافأت للمفجرين الانتحاريين.
Just by bringing the very action,
فقط عن طريق رفع الدعوى،
that bank has stopped doing it, and indeed,
البنك توقف عن فعلها، وبالفعل
the powers that be around the world, which for real politic
القوه التي من حول العالم، التي بالفعل هي اسباب سياسيه
reasons before, couldn't actually deal with this issue,
من قبل، لم تكن قادره على التعاطي مع هذه المشكله.
because there was lots of competing interests,
بسسب ان هناك الكثير من التنافس في المصالح،
have actually closed down those loopholes in the banking system.
قامت بالفعل بإغلاق تلك الثغرات في الجهاز المصرفي.
There's another case called the McDonald case,
هناك قضيه اخرى تدعى قضيه ماكدونالد
where some victims of Semtex, of the Provisional IRA bombings,
حيث أن بعض الضحايا لسيمتكس، لتفجيرات الجيش الجمهوري الايرلندي المؤقت،
which were supplied by Gaddafi, sued,
الذي كان ممولاًً من القذافي، تمت مقاضاته
and that action has led to amazing things for new Libya.
و أدى هذا الإجراء إلى الأشياء المدهشة ليبيا الجديدة.
New Libya has been compassionate towards those victims,
ليبيا الجديده اصبحت متعاطفه مع هؤلاء الضحايا
and started taking it -- so it started a whole new dialogue there.
وبدأت بأخذها -- بدأ حوار جديد كليا هناك.
But the problem is, we need more and more support
لكن المشكله هي، نحن نحتاج المزيد من الدعم
for these ideas and cases.
لهذه الافكار والقضايا.
Civil affairs and civil society initiatives.
ومبادرات من الشؤون المدنية والمجتمع المدني.
A good one is in Somalia. There's a war on piracy.
فكرة جيدة في الصومال. هناك حرب على القرصنة.
If anyone thinks you can have a war on piracy
اذا كان هنالك اي شخص يعتقد انه بالإمكان شن حرب على القرصنه
like a war on terrorism and beat it, you're wrong.
مثل الحرب على الإزهاب والتغلب عليها، انت مخطئ
What we're trying to do there is turn pirates to fisherman.
ما نحاول نحن فعله هناك هو تحويل القراصنه الى صيادين.
They used to be fisherman, of course,
لقد كانوا صيادين في السابق، طبعا،
but we stole their fish and dumped a load of toxic waste
لكننا سرقنا سمكهم والقينا مكانها بشحنات من المخلفات السامه
in their water, so what we're trying to do is create
في مياههم، اذا ما نحاول فعله نحن هو خلق
security and employment by bringing a coastguard
أمن وعمل من خلال جلب خفر السواحل
along with the fisheries industry, and I can guarantee you,
جنبا إلى جنب مع صناعة الصيد، واستطيع ان اؤكد لكم،
as that builds, al Shabaab and such likes will not have
بمجرد بناءه ، حركه الشباب وما يشبها لن يكون لديها
the poverty and injustice any longer to prey on those people.
الفقر والظلم لتفترس هؤلاء الناس
These initiatives cost less than a missile,
هذه المبادارات كلفت اقل من صاروخ،
and certainly less than any soldier's life,
وبالتأكيد اقل من حياه جندي،
but more importantly, it takes the war to their homelands,
لكن الأهم، انها تأخذ الحرب الى بلدانهم
and not onto our shore,
وليس الى شواطئهم
and we're looking at the causes.
ونحن ننظر الى هذه الاسباب
The last one I wanted to talk about was dialogue.
اخيرا ما أردت الحديث عنه هو الحوار.
The advantages of dialogue are obvious.
مزايا الحوار واضحة.
It self-educates both sides, enables a better understanding,
انها تعليم ذاتي لكلا الطرفين، تمكن من فهم افضل
reveals the strengths and weaknesses,
تكشف نقاط القوه والضعف،
and yes, like some of the speakers before,
و نعم، مثل بعض المتحدثين سابقا،
the shared vulnerability does lead to trust, and
مشاركه الضعف يؤدي الى الثقه، و
it does then become, that process, part of normalization.
تصبح، هذه العمليه، جزء من العوده للطبيعه.
But it's not an easy road. After the bomb,
لكنه طريق ليس بسهل، بعد التفجير
the victims are not into this.
الضحايا لن يكون لهم نيه في ذلك
There's practical problems.
هناك مشاكل عمليه.
It's politically risky for the protagonists
انها تمثل مخاطرة سياسيه لابطال الروايه
and for the interlocutors. On one occasion
وعلى المتحاورين. في مناسبة واحدة
I was doing it, every time I did a point that they didn't like,
انا كنت افعلها، وفي كل مره اقول نقطه لم تكن تعجبهم
they actually threw stones at me,
كانوا يرموني بالحجاره بالفعل
and when I did a point they liked,
وعندما اقول نقطه تعجبهم،
they starting shooting in the air, equally not great. (Laughter)
كانوا يطلقون الرصاص في الهواء، في كل الحالتين ليس عظيماً
Whatever the point, it gets to the heart of the problem,
مهما كانت النقطه، فإنها ستصل الى قلب المشكله
you're doing it, you're talking to them.
نحن نفعلها، نحن نتحدث اليهم
Now, I just want to end with saying, if we follow reason,
الان، اريد ان انهي بمقوله، اذا اتبعنا السبب
we realize that I think we'd all say that we want to
سندرك أننا سنقول ان ما نريد هو
have a perception of terrorism which is not just a pure
لدينا تصور للإرهاب الذي هو ليس محض
military perception of it.
تصور عسكري له.
We need to foster more
نحن بحاجه الى مزيد من التعزيز
modern and asymmetrical responses to it.
رد فعل حضاري و لا متماثل له.
This isn't about being soft on terrorism.
الأمر لا يتعلق بالتساهل مع الإرهاب.
It's about fighting them on contemporary battlefields.
بل هو محاربتهم في ميادين القتال المعاصره.
We must foster innovation, as I've said.
يجب علينا تشجيع الابتكار وكما قلت.
Governments are receptive. It won't come from those dusty corridors.
الحكومات متقبله . لكنها لن تأتي من تلك الممرات المتربة.
The private sector has a role.
القطاع الخاص له دور.
The role we could do right now is going away
الدور الذي يمكننا فعله الان هو الذهاب بعيدا
and looking at how we can support victims around the world
ومعرفه كيف يمكننا مسانده الضحايا في انحاء العالم
to bring initiatives.
لجلب المبادرات
If I was to leave you with some big questions here which
إذا كان لي أن أترككم مع بعض الأسئلة الكبيرة التي هنا
may change one's perception to it, and who knows what
التي قد تغير نظره الشخص، ومن يدري ماهي
thoughts and responses will come out of it,
الافكار والردود التي ستنتج منها،
but did myself and my terrorist group actually need
لكن هل أنا شخصيا ومجموعتي الارهابيه نحتاج
to blow you up to make our point?
لنفجر انفسنا حتى تصل لكم فكرتنا
We have to ask ourselves these questions, however unpalatable.
يجب علينا ان نسأل انفسنا هذه الاسئله، ومع ان ذلك غير مستساغ
Have we been ignoring an injustice or a humanitarian
هل كنا نتجاهل الظلم او صراع
struggle somewhere in the world?
إنساني في مكان ما في العالم؟
What if, actually, engagement on poverty and injustice
وماذا لو، بالفعل، مشاركتنا في الفقر والظلم
is exactly what the terrorists wanted us to do?
هي بالفعل مايريده الارهابيين منا ان نفعله؟
What if the bombs are just simply wake-up calls for us?
ماذا لو كانت التفجيرات نداء صحوه لنا؟
What happens if that bomb went off
ماذا يحصل لو ان القنبله انفجرت
because we didn't have any thoughts and things in place
بسبب اننا لم يكن لدينا افكار واشياء في مكانها
to allow dialogue to deal with these things and interaction?
لتسمح بالحوار للتعامل مع هذه الأمور والتفاعل؟
What is definitely uncontroversial
ما هو غير قابل للجدال بالتأكيد
is that, as I've said, we've got to stop being reactive,
هو، كما قلت، يجب علينا ان نتوقف عن ردود الفعل
and more proactive, and I just want to leave you
ونصبح لدينا رد فعل استباقي، أريد فقط ان اترككم
with one idea, which is that
مع فكره واحده فقط
it's a provocative question for you to think about,
انه سؤال لرد الفعل الاستباقي لتفكروا فيه
and the answer will require sympathy with the devil.
والجواب يتطلب التعاطف مع الشيطان
It's a question that's been tackled by many great thinkers
انه سؤال تناوله العديد من المفكرين العظماء
and writers: What if society actually needs crisis to change?
والكتّاب، ماذا لو بالفعل المجتمع بحاجه الى ازمه ليتغير؟
What if society actually needs terrorism
ماذا لو بالفعل المجتمع يحتاج ارهابيين
to change and adapt for the better?
ليتغير ويتكيف للأفضل؟
It's those Bulgakov themes, it's that picture of Jesus
في هذه المواضيع للكاتب بولياكوف ،فإن تلك الصوره لعيسى
and the Devil hand in hand in Gethsemane
مع الشرير يدا بيد في طور زيتا
walking into the moonlight.
يسيرون تحت ضوء القمر
What it would mean is that humans,
مايعنيه هذا للبشريه،
in order to survive in development,
من أجل البقاء في التطور،
quite Darwinian spirit here,
روح الداروينيه هنا،
inherently must dance with the devil.
بطبيعتها، يجب الرقص مع الشرير.
A lot of people say that communism was defeated
وهناك الكثير من الناس يقولون أن الشيوعية قد هُزمت
by the Rolling Stones. It's a good theory.
من قبل الرولينج ستون، انها نظريه جيده
Maybe the Rolling Stones has a place in this.
ربما الرولينج ستون لها مكان في هذا.
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Music) (Applause)
(موسيقى) (تصفيق)
Bruno Giussani: Thank you. (Applause)
شكراً (تصفيق)